<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">7418767</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(20)31486-9</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e04642</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e04642</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Virtual screening, molecular docking studies and DFT calculations of FDA approved compounds similar to the non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI) efavirenz</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
          <name>
            <surname>Jordaan</surname>
            <given-names>Maryam A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>maryamamrajordaan@gmail.com</email>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x2217;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
          <name>
            <surname>Ebenezer</surname>
            <given-names>Oluwakemi</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
          <name>
            <surname>Damoyi</surname>
            <given-names>Nkululeko</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
          <name>
            <surname>Shapi</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">Faculty of Natural Science, Department of Chemistry, Mangosuthu University of Technology, 511 Mangosuthu Highway, Durban, 4000, South Africa</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x2217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>maryamamrajordaan@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
\t\t\t\t\t\tpub-type="epub">.-->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2020</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <fpage>e04642</fpage>
      <lpage>e04642</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company\'s public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="abs0010">
        <p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) was confirmed as the causative virus of COVID-19 disease, which is currently a worldwide pandemic. Efavirenz, a non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI), is one of the most potent chemical compounds proposed to treat COVID-19 infection. We, therefore, performed virtual screening on FDA approved drugs that are similar to the efavirenz moiety. Subsequently, the compounds were subjected to screening by analyzing their drug-likeness, such as Lipinski\'s rule of five and ADMET properties. Molecular docking study revealed that Met165, His41, His163, and Phe140 were important interacting residues for COVID-19 main protease receptor-ligand interaction. Five top-ranked compounds, podophyllotoxin, oxacillin, lovastatin, simvastatin, and gefitinib, were selected by virtual screening and docking studies. The highest occupied molecular (HOMO) orbital, lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO) and energy gap values was calculated using density functional theory (DFT). The results of the study showed that lovastatin and simvastatin might be considered as lead compounds for further development for COVID-19 main protease inhibitors.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015">
        <p>Pharmaceutical chemistry; Theoretical chemistry, COVID-19; NNRTI; Virtual screening; Efavirenz; HIV</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Pharmaceutical chemistry</kwd>
        <kwd>Theoretical chemistry</kwd>
        <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
        <kwd>NNRTI</kwd>
        <kwd>Virtual screening</kwd>
        <kwd>Efavirenz</kwd>
        <kwd>HIV</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec1">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p id="p0010">The novel coronavirus (COVID-19)was identified in the Hubei Province of China in 2019, and, today, over half a million people are currently infected globally with more than 20 834 deaths [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Coronaviruses are positively stranded RNA viruses that cause respiratory, enteric, and central nervous system diseases. The recent novel COVID-19 virus is considered a betacoronavirus alongside severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and the Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS-CoV). More also, additional sequence alignment revealed a 96.1% comparison to the sequence of the main protease between COVID-19 and SARS-CoV [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The crystal structure of the COVID-19 main protease in complex with a peptidomimetic inhibitor (PDB code <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0010">6LU7</ext-link>) is presented in (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
). Viruses like the COVID-19 mutate rapidly rendering it difficult to design an appropriate treatment. Previous studies demonstrated that the main protease of SARS-CoV is essential for the life cycle of the virus, and considered to be an attractive target for drug development [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Drugs that target conservative protease are usually capable of preventing the replication and proliferation of the virus while reducing the risk of mutation mediated drug-resistance [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>The model structure of the COVID-19 main protease in complex with a peptidomimetic inhibitor (PDB; 6LU7).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure&#xA0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0015">Recent positive data highlights the application of a cocktail of antivirals, including two antiretroviral components lopinavir and ritonavir, by doctors in Thailand who were able to cure a COVID-19 patient using this treatment. These two antiretroviral components are protease inhibitors designed to block HIV viral replication and holds that these drugs could do the same for COVID-19 [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
      <p id="p0020">Furthermore, a similar study conducted by Beck and co-workers (2019) highlighted the application of a Molecule Transformer-Drug Target Interaction (MT-DTI) model to identify possible existing compounds to treat COVID-19. They predicted antiretroviral medication for HIV as the best chemical compounds to treat COVID-19, i.e.: atazanavir, efavirenz, ritonavir, and dolutegraviran [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Shaha and coworkers also identified a range of ARVs, including efavirenz see <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>
as a potential treatment for COVID-19 [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Confirming ARVs as a potential therapy, Yan Li and his team at the Sichuan University and Army Medical University in China (2020) identified, <italic>via</italic> a large chemical screening, four molecular drugs with high-affinity to a coronavirus protein. Of these, two were ARVs, i.e. bictegravir and nelfinavir. The other two were Prulifloxacin, a chemotherapeutic antibiotic, and Tegobuvi, an antiviral drug used in the treatment of Hepatitis C infection [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Contini (2020) also used virtual screening and identified four ARVs to treat COVID-19, i.e. indinavir, lopinavir, and atazanavir and cobicistat [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Furthermore, three types of <italic>in silico</italic> DTI prediction methods are used, i.e. molecular docking, similarity-based, and deep learning-based [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The selection of the efavirenz scaffold was based on the following factors: firstly, ARVs have been utilized as an antiviral regime for patients infected with the coronavirus and secondly, <italic>in silico</italic> DTI predictions identified antiretroviral (ARV), efavirenz, a non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI) as one of the most potent chemical compounds with the inhibitory potency with <italic>Kd</italic> of 199.17 nM against the COVID-19 main protease [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Optimized structure of efavirenz.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#xA0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0025">In this study, virtual screening, also called <italic>in silico</italic> screening, was chosen to provide a rapid and inexpensive method for the discovery of FDA approved active compounds exhibiting a scaffold similar to efavirenz, which binds to the active pocket of COVID-19 main protease. Virtual screening and molecular docking results revealed promising potential hit compounds for COVID-19 main protease inhibition. Density functional theory (DFT) was used further to calculate the orbital energy value and the energy gap.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="sec2.1">
        <label>2.1</label>
        <title>Ligand preparation</title>
        <p id="p0030">The active compounds similar to efavirenz were retrieved from the zinc database [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Protocol constraints such as biogenic data, FDA approval, anodyne, and sell data were set to filter out the compounds. A total of 232 molecules were retrieved and prepared for docking by subjecting to energy minimization using the Open Babel module in PyRx program.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.2">
        <label>2.2</label>
        <title>Receptor preparation</title>
        <p id="p0035">The crystal structure of COVID-19 main protease (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6lu7" id="intref0015">6lu7</ext-link>) and the native ligand was downloaded from RCSB with a resolution of 2.16 &#xC5; [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Discovery Studio Visualizer software was used to prepare the receptor for docking. The native ligand and water molecules were deleted from the crystal structure of COVID-19 main protease. Molecular docking was performed with AutoDock 4.2 module implemented in PyRx 0.8 using the empirical free energy force field and Lamarckian genetic algorithm conformational search with the default parameters [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The grid on the ligand-binding site of the protein was centered at the binding site of X = -20, Y = 13, Z = 47, and the grid dimensions were 40 &#xD7; 30 &#xD7; 62 &#xC5;<sup>3</sup>. For further analysis, 43 compounds with a lowest binding affinity (&lt;-7.0 kcal/mol) were selected. Protein-ligands interaction was analyzed using Discovery Studio Visualizer software.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.3">
        <label>2.3</label>
        <title>Physicochemical and ADME biochemical prediction</title>
        <p id="p0040">Selected compounds from the molecular docking analysis were evaluated for their drug-like behavior through analysis of pharmacokinetic parameters required for absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion (ADME). QikProp module and Lipinski\'s rule integrated into virtual screening workflow (filtering option) of Schr&#xF6;dinger software was employed for calculations. We discarded 20 compounds, which were predicted to violate Lipinski\'s rule of five and, also fall out of optimum range for partition coefficient (QPlogPo/w), critical for estimation of absorption within the body; cell permeability (QPPCaco), a key factor governing drug metabolism and its access to biological membranes; QPPMDCK and percentage human oral absorption. Hence, 27 compounds were observed to have physicochemical and pharmacokinetic parameters within the acceptable range.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.4">
        <label>2.4</label>
        <title>Density functional theory</title>
        <p id="p0045">Density functional theory (DFT) is a computational quantum mechanical modeling method used to examine the electronic structure and also to investigate the interactions involved between the receptors and the ligands. The electronic and structural properties of the five best hit compounds were calculated using the Becke3-Lee-Yang-Parr (B3LYP) method with the 6&#x2013;31G(d,p) basis set aided by Gaussian 09. The calculated parameters used in this study include the highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) and the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO) energies, electron affinity, and electrophilicity index. The molecular electrostatic potential surfaces (MEPs) were obtained from the population analysis calculations and visualized using Gauss View. These parameters play an influential role in explaining the magnitude of ligands interaction in the binding pocket of COVID-19 main protease.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.5">
        <label>2.5</label>
        <title>Molecular dynamics</title>
        <p id="p0050">To validate the stability of the hit compound, we have performed molecular dynamics simulation using NAMD full setup through the MDWeb interface. The simulation process includes cleaning of the protein structure; fixing of side chains; addition of hydrogen atoms; neutralization, the addition of a solvent box and heating solvent to 300 K; reducing the restraints to just the protein backbone and minimization and equilibration of the system to finally achieve the structure prepared by simulation. To achieve a dry trajectory for the simulated protein, water molecules and ions were removed from the system.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p id="p0055">To validate our docking protocol, we redocked native ligand and the selected 27 compounds, into the binding pocket of COVID-19 main protease using AutoDock 4.2 module in PyRx tool with default parameters. Moreover, the binding affinity of the native ligand was selected as a benchmark. Five of these compounds exhibited superior binding affinity as well as good interaction compared to efavirenz and the native ligand (-6.5 and -7.4 kcal/mol respectively), thus selected for visual analysis. Refer to <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#xA0;1</xref>
for full data.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Physicochemical and ADMET descriptors of efavirenz and the 27 dock compounds calculated from QikProp.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0210">Table&#xA0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Molecule</th><th>Binding Affinity</th><th>MW</th><th>HBD</th><th>HBA</th><th>QPpolrz</th><th>QPlogPC16</th><th>QPlogPoct</th><th>QPlogPw</th><th>QPlogPo/w</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Picato</td><td>-7.0</td><td>430.54</td><td>3</td><td>8.15</td><td>43.941</td><td>12.43</td><td>23.41</td><td>13.578</td><td>3.235</td></tr><tr><td>Gefitinib</td><td>-7.7</td><td>446.908</td><td>1</td><td>7.7</td><td>44.759</td><td>13.302</td><td>20.35</td><td>10.804</td><td>4.355</td></tr><tr><td>Eht0201</td><td>-5.6</td><td>278.31</td><td>0</td><td>7</td><td>29.044</td><td>8.317</td><td>13.427</td><td>8.177</td><td>1.176</td></tr><tr><td>Dicloxacillin</td><td>-7.2</td><td>470.326</td><td>1.25</td><td>7.75</td><td>40.522</td><td>12.4</td><td>20.394</td><td>14.035</td><td>2.52</td></tr><tr><td>Oxacillin</td><td>-7.8</td><td>401.436</td><td>1.25</td><td>7.75</td><td>39.907</td><td>12.236</td><td>20.481</td><td>15.401</td><td>2.364</td></tr><tr><td>Simvastatin</td><td>-7.8</td><td>418.572</td><td>1</td><td>6.7</td><td>45.909</td><td>12.849</td><td>20.603</td><td>9.457</td><td>4.67</td></tr><tr><td>Lovastatin</td><td>-7.6</td><td>404.545</td><td>1</td><td>6.7</td><td>43.257</td><td>12.147</td><td>19.716</td><td>9.281</td><td>4.252</td></tr><tr><td>Hyoscine</td><td>-7.2</td><td>303.357</td><td>0</td><td>6.7</td><td>30.356</td><td>9.009</td><td>13.285</td><td>8.03</td><td>1.247</td></tr><tr><td>(<italic>S</italic>)-Colchicine</td><td>-7.3</td><td>399.443</td><td>1</td><td>7.5</td><td>39.735</td><td>10.7</td><td>18.511</td><td>11.646</td><td>2.586</td></tr><tr><td>(<italic>R</italic>)-Colchicine</td><td>-7.3</td><td>399.443</td><td>1</td><td>7.5</td><td>39.735</td><td>10.7</td><td>18.511</td><td>11.646</td><td>2.586</td></tr><tr><td>Podophyllotoxin</td><td>-7.9</td><td>414.411</td><td>1</td><td>8.45</td><td>37.819</td><td>10.369</td><td>18.665</td><td>11.276</td><td>2.463</td></tr><tr><td>Pentamidine</td><td>-6.5</td><td>340.424</td><td>6</td><td>4.5</td><td>35.113</td><td>14.334</td><td>23.426</td><td>15.09</td><td>2.564</td></tr><tr><td>Altol</td><td>-6.1</td><td>266.339</td><td>4</td><td>6.45</td><td>28.471</td><td>10.176</td><td>18.409</td><td>16.261</td><td>0.172</td></tr><tr><td>Epoprostenol</td><td>-6.7</td><td>352.47</td><td>3</td><td>6.15</td><td>37.05</td><td>12.449</td><td>19.825</td><td>10.511</td><td>3.645</td></tr><tr><td>Pgx</td><td>-6.6</td><td>352.47</td><td>3</td><td>6.15</td><td>36.611</td><td>12.353</td><td>19.839</td><td>10.517</td><td>3.528</td></tr><tr><td>Urso</td><td>-7.2</td><td>392.578</td><td>3</td><td>5.4</td><td>40.054</td><td>11.825</td><td>20.873</td><td>10.957</td><td>3.785</td></tr><tr><td>Chenodal</td><td>-7.2</td><td>392.578</td><td>3</td><td>5.4</td><td>39.956</td><td>11.776</td><td>21.404</td><td>10.922</td><td>3.8</td></tr><tr><td>Degalol</td><td>-7.1</td><td>392.578</td><td>3</td><td>5.4</td><td>40.005</td><td>11.788</td><td>20.906</td><td>10.933</td><td>3.802</td></tr><tr><td>Cholic acid</td><td>-6.9</td><td>408.577</td><td>4</td><td>7.1</td><td>39.864</td><td>12.316</td><td>23.381</td><td>14.035</td><td>2.897</td></tr><tr><td>Enalaprilat</td><td>-7.2</td><td>348.398</td><td>3</td><td>8.5</td><td>36.266</td><td>12.203</td><td>22.246</td><td>15.652</td><td>-0.722</td></tr><tr><td>Piceid</td><td>-7.2</td><td>390.389</td><td>6</td><td>10.75</td><td>35.388</td><td>14.14</td><td>26.981</td><td>21.618</td><td>0.178</td></tr><tr><td>Pfizerpen</td><td>-7.0</td><td>334.389</td><td>1.25</td><td>6.25</td><td>34.46</td><td>10.833</td><td>16.853</td><td>15.782</td><td>1.83</td></tr><tr><td>Sufentanil</td><td>-6.6</td><td>386.551</td><td>0</td><td>6.7</td><td>43.447</td><td>12.783</td><td>17.658</td><td>8.379</td><td>4.055</td></tr><tr><td>Cephalexin</td><td>-6.7</td><td>347.388</td><td>3.25</td><td>7.25</td><td>34.128</td><td>11.614</td><td>20.635</td><td>16.746</td><td>-1.256</td></tr><tr><td>Ampicilin</td><td>-7.3</td><td>349.404</td><td>3.25</td><td>7.25</td><td>34.803</td><td>11.777</td><td>21.321</td><td>19.022</td><td>-1.946</td></tr><tr><td>Omeprazole</td><td>-6.6</td><td>345.415</td><td>1</td><td>8</td><td>35.293</td><td>10.448</td><td>17.167</td><td>13.818</td><td>2.232</td></tr><tr><td>Prazosin</td><td>-7.3</td><td>383.406</td><td>2</td><td>8</td><td>40.055</td><td>11.866</td><td>21.002</td><td>13.528</td><td>2.659</td></tr><tr><td>Efavirenz</td><td>-6.5</td><td>315.679</td><td>1</td><td>3.5</td><td>28.899</td><td>7.837</td><td>13.636</td><td>6.799</td><td>3.516</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Molecule</th><th>QPlogHERG</th><th>QPPCaco</th><th>QPlogBB</th><th>QPPMDCK</th><th>QPlogKp</th><th>QPlogKhsa</th><th>HumanOralAbsorption</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Picato</td><td>-4.186</td><td>628.425</td><td>-0.975</td><td>299.423</td><td>-3.152</td><td>0.4</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Gefitinib</td><td>-7.165</td><td>1049.826</td><td>0.307</td><td>2306.299</td><td>-2.681</td><td>0.367</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Eht0201</td><td>-4.416</td><td>495.631</td><td>-1.037</td><td>231.661</td><td>-3.362</td><td>-0.721</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Dicloxacillin</td><td>-0.661</td><td>22.25</td><td>-1.002</td><td>68.544</td><td>-4.468</td><td>-0.223</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Oxacillin</td><td>-1.777</td><td>15.896</td><td>-1.43</td><td>19.858</td><td>-4.245</td><td>-0.355</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Simvastatin</td><td>-4.736</td><td>652.454</td><td>-1.067</td><td>311.817</td><td>-2.822</td><td>0.783</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Lovastatin</td><td>-4.495</td><td>869.722</td><td>-0.902</td><td>425.43</td><td>-2.58</td><td>0.611</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Hyoscine</td><td>-4.396</td><td>440.051</td><td>0.029</td><td>225.371</td><td>-4.02</td><td>-0.611</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>(<italic>S</italic>)-Colchicine</td><td>-3.08</td><td>927.454</td><td>-0.599</td><td>710.539</td><td>-2.527</td><td>-0.086</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>(<italic>R</italic>)-Colchicine</td><td>-3.08</td><td>927.448</td><td>-0.599</td><td>710.537</td><td>-2.527</td><td>-0.086</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Podophyllotoxin</td><td>-3.94</td><td>1528.112</td><td>-0.418</td><td>782.348</td><td>-2.391</td><td>-0.075</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Pentamidine</td><td>-6.671</td><td>83.493</td><td>-2.728</td><td>33.789</td><td>-7.263</td><td>-0.172</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Altol</td><td>-4.478</td><td>37.094</td><td>-1.169</td><td>33.983</td><td>-5.18</td><td>-0.752</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Epoprostenol</td><td>-3.586</td><td>41.239</td><td>-2.35</td><td>20.05</td><td>-3.668</td><td>0.052</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Pgx</td><td>-3.461</td><td>34.615</td><td>-2.403</td><td>16.592</td><td>-3.828</td><td>0.031</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Urso</td><td>-2.092</td><td>43.15</td><td>-1.5</td><td>21.056</td><td>-4.373</td><td>0.451</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Chenodal</td><td>-2.052</td><td>47.21</td><td>-1.453</td><td>23.205</td><td>-4.297</td><td>0.447</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Degalol</td><td>-2.114</td><td>46.796</td><td>-1.472</td><td>22.985</td><td>-4.304</td><td>0.447</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Cholic acid</td><td>-2.046</td><td>26.197</td><td>-1.757</td><td>12.278</td><td>-4.698</td><td>0.119</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Enalaprilat</td><td>-0.948</td><td>2.211</td><td>-1.324</td><td>1.475</td><td>-5.56</td><td>-0.876</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Piceid</td><td>-5.723</td><td>34.353</td><td>-2.729</td><td>12.939</td><td>-4.199</td><td>-0.742</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Pfizerpen</td><td>-0.36</td><td>17.716</td><td>-1.189</td><td>41.948</td><td>-3.568</td><td>-0.742</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sufentanil</td><td>-6.823</td><td>1666.192</td><td>0.398</td><td>1627.984</td><td>-2.13</td><td>0.257</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Cephalexin</td><td>-2.545</td><td>3.129</td><td>-1.359</td><td>3.188</td><td>-6.505</td><td>-0.631</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Ampicilin</td><td>-1.101</td><td>2.153</td><td>-1.227</td><td>4.537</td><td>-6.339</td><td>-0.909</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Omeprazole</td><td>-5.174</td><td>59.206</td><td>-0.532</td><td>951.724</td><td>-1.969</td><td>-0.242</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Prazosin</td><td>-5.709</td><td>891.968</td><td>-0.802</td><td>437.204</td><td>-2.371</td><td>0.061</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Efavirenz</td><td>-4.343</td><td>1524.372</td><td>0.075</td><td>6408.891</td><td>-2.535</td><td>0.267</td><td>3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>M.W &#x2013; molecular weight; log&#x2009;S<sub><italic>wat</italic></sub> - aqueous solubility (-6.5&#x2013;0.5); log&#x2009;<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>HSA</italic></sub>&#xA0;- logarithm of predicted binding constant to human serum albumin (-1.5&#x2013;1.5); QPlogPw &#x2013; water/gas partition (4.0&#x2013;45.0); QPlogPC16 &#x2013;hexadecane/gas partition (4.0&#x2013;18); log&#x2009;BB - logarithm of predicted blood/brain barrier partition coefficient (-3.0-1.2); Caco-2 - cell membrane permeability (&lt;25 poor &gt;500 good); HBA - number of hydrogen bond acceptors (2&#x2013;20); HBD number of hydrogen bond donors (0&#x2013;6); QP<sub><italic>polrz</italic></sub> - predicted polarizability (13&#x2013;70); log&#x2009;<italic>HERG</italic>&#xA0;the predicted IC<sub>50</sub>&#xA0;value for the blockage of HERG K<sup>+</sup>&#xA0;channels (concern below -5); QPPMDCK &#x2013; predicted MDCK cell permeability in nm/sec (&lt;25 poor &gt;500 great); log&#x2009;<italic>K</italic><sub>p</sub>&#xA0;- predicted skin permeability and 95% of drugs: (-8 to -1);, log&#x2009;<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>HSA</italic></sub> - logarithm of predicted binding constant to human serum albumin (-1.5&#x2013;1.5), Human Oral Absorption &#x2013; 1-low, 2-medium, 3- high.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0060">The five selected compounds include simvastatin and lovastatin, HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor; oxacillin, a penicillinase-resistant &#x3B2;-lactam; podophyllotoxin, which is an antimitotic; and Gefitinib an epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) inhibitor [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The identification of the key contributing residues in the binding pocket of the C19MP was performed using the Discovery Studio Visualizer.</p>
      <p id="p0065">The docked results showed that inhibitors swing between the space of hydrophobic residues; Met165, His41, Met49, Cys145, His165 and Leu27 which gave more conformational freedom, on the one hand; residues Glu166, His163, Thr26, Phe140, Thr190, His164 and Gln189, Gln143 showed hydrogen bond interaction with the ligands. Also, protein-ligands interaction showed that the presence of naphthalene, quinazoline, isoxazole, benzyl, and tetrahydropyran rings played an important role. The details of the structures with the best docking scores are provided in Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>
.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Structures of the FDA approved active compounds exhibiting a scaffold similar to efavirenz.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#xA0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of C19MP (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0060">6LU7</ext-link>) interactions with the native ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0025">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0030">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx3_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0035">Image 3</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic interaction <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx4_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0040">Image 4</alt-text></inline-graphic> carbon-hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Figure&#xA0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0070">The quinazoline ring of gefitinib (b.e = 7.7 kcal/mol) formed &#x3C0;-alkyl interaction with Met165; meanwhile, one of the <italic>N</italic> atom donors in the ring formed a conventional hydrogen bond with the <italic>O</italic> atom acceptor of conserved residue His41, with bond distance (b.d) of 2.50 &#xC5;. Besides, the amine group formed a conventional hydrogen bond with His164 (b.d = 2.66 &#xC5; and bond angle, (b.a) = 131.02<sup>o</sup> and 153.7<sup>o</sup> respectively). Carbon hydrogen bonds are formed between the morphine ring, methyl group and, residue Phe140 and Thr190 (b.d = 3.69, and 3.57 &#xC5;; b.a = 103.12 and 97.39<sup>o</sup> respectively). Apart from H-bonding, the <italic>Cl</italic> atom at the R<sub>5</sub> position of the benzyl ring formed hydrophobic interaction with Leu27. These hydrophobic and H-bonding interactions of C19MP with the ligand may account for the good binding affinity (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;5</xref>
).<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of C19MP (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0065">6LU7</ext-link>) interactions with gefitinib.<inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0050">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0055">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx5_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0060">Image 5</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic interaction <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx6_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0065">Image 6</alt-text></inline-graphic> carbon-hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Figure&#xA0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0075">The amine group and the <italic>O</italic> atom of the isoxazole ring (oxacillin, b.e = 7.8 kcal/mol) exhibit H-bond with Thr190 and Gln189 (b.d = 2.32 and 3.40 &#xC5;; b.a = 137.72, 144.5 and 91.7<sup>o</sup> respectively). Meanwhile, Met165 was sandwiched between the isoxazole ring and the methyl substituent (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;6</xref>
B). The phenyl group attached to the isoxazole ring interacts hydrophobically with Pro168 also contributes to the stabilization of the complex. Other residues like Ala19, Gln192, Agr188, Gln189, His164, 163, Gly143, Ser144, and Leu141 make close contact with the ligand without interactions (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;6</xref>A).<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>2D representation (<bold>A</bold>) and 3D representation (<bold>B</bold>) of oxacillin in the binding pocket of C19MP (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0070">6LU7</ext-link>) <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0075">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0080">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx7_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0085">Image 7</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic interaction <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx3_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0090">Image 3</alt-text></inline-graphic> carbon-hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0095">Figure&#xA0;6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0080">Moreover, His41 and Cys145 interacted with methyl group substituent, which was accompanied by one conventional H-bonding between the carboxyl oxygen atom and Cys145 (b.d = 3.55 &#xC5;; b.a = 107.66 and 108.0<sup>o</sup> respectively), whereas the amine linker horizontally formed H-bond with Glu166 (b.d = 2.70 &#xC5;, b.a = 128.93, 117.4<sup>o</sup>).</p>
      <p id="p0085">In the docked complex of lovastatin (b.e = 7.6 kcal/mol), the <italic>O</italic> atom of tetrahydropyran moiety formed a conventional H- bond with <italic>N</italic> atom of Glu166 (b.d = 2.64 &#xC5;, b.a = 111.03 and 104.82<sup>o</sup> respectively), the carbonyl oxygen atom interact with the <italic>N</italic> atom of His163 <italic>via</italic> H-bonding (b.d = 2.13 &#xC5; and b.a = 115.19 and 142.06<sup>o</sup> respectively), meanwhile the secondary hydroxyl group exhibited an H-bond network with Phe140 (b.a = 2.82 &#xC5;, b.a = 135.37 and 120.80<sup>o</sup>, respectively).</p>
      <p id="p0090">The naphthalene ring and the methyl group, which is adjacent to methyl butanoate, formed &#x3C0;-alkyl interaction with the side chain of Met165 and His41; the carbonyl oxygen group of methyl butanoate formed H-bonding interaction with the side chain of Cys145. From the above results, it can be pointed out, that H-bond interactions with the key binding residues Gln166, His163, Phe140, and Cys145 are major motivators for the stabilization of the inhibitor within the catalytic pocket. In contrast, hydrophobic interactions played a minor role (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;7</xref>
).<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#xA0;7</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of COVID-19 main protease (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0075">6LU7</ext-link>) interactions with lovastatin<inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0100">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0105">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx8_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0110">Image 8</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic interaction <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx9_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0115">Image 9</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0120">Figure&#xA0;7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0095">The <italic>O</italic> atom, carbonyl oxygen group, as well as Sp<sup>3</sup> hybridized carbon in the furanone ring (podophyllotoxin, b.e = 7.7 kcal/mol)<bold>)</bold>, interact with residue His163, Cys145, and Phe140 via H-bond (b.d = 1.91, 3.45, and 3.20 &#xC5;; b.a = 99.1, 157.3 and 108.0<sup>o</sup>, respectively. The imidazole ring of conserved residue His41 was sandwiched between the phenyl ring and the <italic>meta</italic>-OCH<sub>3</sub> substituent on the phenyl ring; this was accompanied by one hydrophobic interaction. These interesting interactions potentially deepen the binding strength of podophyllotoxin to the C19MP receptor and seem to be critical (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;8</xref>
).<fig id="fig8"><label>Figure&#xA0;8</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of COVID-19 main protease (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0080">6LU7</ext-link>) interactions with podophyllotoxin.<inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0125">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0130">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx10_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0135">Image 10</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx11_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0140">Image 11</alt-text></inline-graphic> interaction hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0145">Figure&#xA0;8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0100">A binding affinity score of &#x2212;7.8 kcal/mol was obtained for the docking of simvastatin in the binding site of C19MP (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;9</xref>
) refer to supporting information, which also indicates strong interactions between the ligand and the receptor. The carbonyl oxygen group and the <italic>O</italic> atom in the tetrahydropyran ring interact with His163 and Glu166 via H-bond (b.d = 2.21, 2.67 &#xC5;; b.a = 115.6, 125.1<sup>o</sup>, respectively). The naphthalene group extends into the hydrophobic pocket potentiating the ligand-receptor interaction (His 41 and Met165); the ring stacks vertically with the imidazole ring of His41 forming a &#x3C0;-&#x3C0; T-shaped interaction. Additional stability to this complex is afforded by the formation of a hydrogen bond interaction between the carbonyl oxygen atom of dimethylbutanoate and residue Cys145.<fig id="fig9"><label>Figure&#xA0;9</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of C19MP (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0085">6LU7</ext-link>) interactions with simvastatin. <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0150">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0155">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx3_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0160">Image 3</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic interaction <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx11_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0165">Image 11</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0170">Figure&#xA0;9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <p id="p0105">The presence of a dimethyl substituent also assists with strong binding inside the active site of C19MP by forming hydrophobic interactions with residues His41, Cys145, and Met49, respectively. Physicochemical and ADMET descriptors of the five best dock compounds are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#xA0;2</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Physicochemical and ADMET descriptors of the six best dock compounds from QikProp.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0215">Table&#xA0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Zinc Id</th><th>mol_MW</th><th>HBD</th><th>HBA</th><th>QPpolrz</th><th>QPlogPC16</th><th>QPlogPoct</th><th>QPlogPw</th><th>QPlogPo/w</th><th>QPlogS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Gefitinib</td><td>446.908</td><td>1</td><td>7.7</td><td>44.759</td><td>13.302</td><td>20.35</td><td>10.804</td><td>4.355</td><td>-5.261</td></tr><tr><td>Oxacillin</td><td>401.436</td><td>1.25</td><td>7.75</td><td>39.907</td><td>12.236</td><td>20.481</td><td>15.401</td><td>2.364</td><td>-3.365</td></tr><tr><td>Lovastatin</td><td>404.545</td><td>1</td><td>6.7</td><td>43.257</td><td>12.147</td><td>19.716</td><td>9.281</td><td>4.252</td><td>-5.796</td></tr><tr><td>Podophyllotoxin</td><td>414.411</td><td>1</td><td>8.45</td><td>37.819</td><td>10.369</td><td>18.665</td><td>11.276</td><td>2.463</td><td>-3.541</td></tr><tr><td>Simvastatin</td><td>418.572</td><td>1</td><td>6</td><td>45.909</td><td>12.849</td><td>20.603</td><td>9.457</td><td>4.67</td><td>-7.058</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Zinc Id</th><th>QPlogHERG</th><th>QPPCaco</th><th>QPlogBB</th><th>QPPMDCK</th><th>QPlogKp</th><th>QPlogKhsa</th><th>Human Oral Absorption</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Gefitinib</td><td>-7.165</td><td>1049.83</td><td>0.307</td><td>2306.299</td><td>-2.681</td><td>0.367</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Oxacillin</td><td>-1.777</td><td>15.896</td><td>-1.43</td><td>19.858</td><td>-4.245</td><td>-0.355</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Lovastatin</td><td>-4.495</td><td>869.722</td><td>-0.902</td><td>425.43</td><td>-2.58</td><td>0.611</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Podophyllotoxin</td><td>-3.94</td><td>1528.11</td><td>-0.418</td><td>782.348</td><td>-2.391</td><td>-0.075</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Simvastatin</td><td>-4.736</td><td>652.454</td><td>-1.067</td><td>311.817</td><td>-2.822</td><td>0.783</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>M.W &#x2013; molecular weight; log&#x2009;S<sub><italic>wat</italic></sub> - aqueous solubility (-6.5&#x2013;0.5); log&#x2009;<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>HSA</italic></sub> - logarithm of predicted binding constant to human serum albumin (-1.5&#x2013;1.5); QPlogPw &#x2013; water/gas partition (4.0&#x2013;45.0); QPlogPC16 &#x2013;hexadecane/gas partition (4.0&#x2013;18); log&#x2009;BB - logarithm of predicted blood/brain barrier partition coefficient (-3.0-1.2); Caco-2 - cell membrane permeability (&lt;25 poor &gt;500 good); HBA - number of hydrogen bond acceptors (2&#x2013;20); HBD number of hydrogen bond donors (0&#x2013;6); QP<sub><italic>polrz</italic></sub> - predicted polarizability (13&#x2013;70); log&#x2009;<italic>HERG</italic> the predicted IC<sub>50</sub> value for the blockage of HERG K<sup>+</sup>&#xA0;channels (concern below -5); QPPMDCK &#x2013; predicted MDCK cell permeability in nm/sec (&lt;25 poor &gt;500 great); log&#x2009;<italic>K</italic><sub>p</sub>- predicted skin permeability and 95% of drugs: (-8&#x2014;1); log&#x2009;<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>HSA</italic></sub> - logarithm of predicted binding constant to human serum albumin (-1.5&#x2013;1.5), Human Oral Absorption &#x2013; 1-low, 2-medium, 3- high.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p id="p0110">Furthermore, to validate the docked results of the hit compounds, we performed MD simulations on the COVID-19 main protease and re-docked all the five compounds. The re-docked results revealed an increase in the binding affinity of simvastatin and lovastatin (8.2 and 7.9 kcal/mol), respectively. Surprisingly, there was a decrease in the binding affinity of podophyllotoxin (7.7 kcal/mol), and the binding affinity of oxacillin and gefitinib (7.7 kcal/mol) remained constant. Interestingly<bold>,</bold> the ligands were bound inside the active site of a similar pose and also formed interaction with more residues, mainly through H-bonding <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;10</xref>
.<fig id="fig10"><label>Figure&#xA0;10</label><caption><p>2D representation of the hit compounds in the binding pocket of C19MP after molecular dynamics (PDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6LU7" id="intref0090">6LU7</ext-link>) <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0175">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic> protein <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0180">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic> ligand <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx12_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0185">Image 12</alt-text></inline-graphic> hydrophobic interaction <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx3_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0190">Image 3</alt-text></inline-graphic> carbon-hydrogen bond.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0195">Figure&#xA0;10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
      <sec id="sec3.1">
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Density functional theory</title>
        <p id="p0115">Frontier molecular orbitals of five-hit compounds specify a crucial role of charge-transfer interactions with the binding site of COVID-19 main protease. The higher HOMO value denotes a molecule with a good electron donor, whereas a lower value implies a weak electron acceptor. Furthermore, a smaller energy gap between the LUMO and HOMO energies has a considerable influence on the intermolecular charge transfer and bioactivity of molecules. Thus, a wide energy gap observed in the hit molecules negatively affect the electron to move from the HOMO to the LUMO, which subsequently led to a weak affinity of the inhibitor for COVID-19 main protease. The E<sub>gap</sub> value decreases according to the following<bold>:</bold> oxacillin (0.1021eV) <bold>&gt;</bold> podophyllotoxin (0.0145eV) &gt; gefitinib (0.0351eV) &gt; simvastatin (0.0230eV) &gt; lovastatin (0.0145eV). Hence, the reactivity order increases according to: oxacillin (0.1021eV) <bold>&gt;</bold> podophyllotoxin (0.0410eV) &gt; gefitinib (0.0351eV) &gt; simvastatin (0.0230eV) &gt; lovastatin (0.0145eV) where the most reactive is clearly lovastatin (0.0145eV). The order of reactivity increases conforms with the decreases in energy gap values. The chemical potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mtext>&#x3BC;</mml:mtext></mml:math></inline-formula>) indicate negative values for all the compounds, which implies good stability, and the formation of a stable complex with the receptor. Also, lovastatin and simvastatin have the least hardness values (<bold>&#x3B7;)</bold>, among the hit molecules and which correlated with the trend of molecular docking (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#xA0;3</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Frontier molecular orbital energies (eV) and global reactivity descriptors.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0220">Table&#xA0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Entry</th><th>Zinc ID</th><th>E (I)</th><th>E (A)</th><th>E (A-I)</th><th>&#x3B7;</th><th>&#x3BC;</th><th>&#x3A9;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Gefitinib</td><td>-0.1427</td><td>-0.1076</td><td>0.0351</td><td>0.0176</td><td>-0.1252</td><td>0.4453</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Oxacillin</td><td>-0.1503</td><td>-0.0482</td><td>0.1021</td><td>0.0601</td><td>-0.0993</td><td>0.0820</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Lovastatin</td><td>-0.1930</td><td>-0.1785</td><td>0.0145</td><td>0.0072</td><td>-0.1858</td><td>2.3973</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Podophyllotoxin</td><td>-0.1213</td><td>-0.0803</td><td>0.0410</td><td>0.0070</td><td>-0.1008</td><td>0.7258</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Simvastatin</td><td>-0.2142</td><td>-0.1912</td><td>0.0230</td><td>0.0115</td><td>-0.2027</td><td>1.7864</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p id="p0120">The graphic results from DFT calculations are presented in <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;11</xref>
. The red and green parts represent the cloud density of frontier orbital at HOMO or LUMO states. Finally, by comparing the values of molecular orbital energies (eV), global reactivity descriptors, and binding affinities value of five-hit compounds, simvastatin, and lovastatin may be considered as potential COVID-19 main protease inhibitors.<fig id="fig11"><label>Figure&#xA0;11</label><caption><p>HOMO and LUMO plots of the hit compounds.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0200">Figure&#xA0;11</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr11_lrg"/></fig></p>
        <p id="p0125">The molecular electrostatic potential (MEP) surface provides details about charge distribution and also predicts reactive sites for electrophilic and nucleophilic attack in a compound. Meanwhile, the MEP surface of simvastatin and lovastatin were evaluated using the DFT/b3lyp method as shown in <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;11</xref> most negative regions are shown by red, most positive regions in blue, and zero potential regions are visualized in green. MEP mapped surface of simvastatin range from &#x2212;0.0678 a.u (deepest red) to 0.0678 a.u (deepest blue) and lovastatin range from &#x2212;0.0672 a.u (deepest red) to 0.0672 a.u (deepest blue) <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Figure&#xA0;12</xref>
.<fig id="fig12"><label>Figure&#xA0;12</label><caption><p>Molecular electrostatic surfaces (A) simvastatin and (B) lovastatin.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0205">Figure&#xA0;12</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr12_lrg"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec4">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p id="p0130">In this research paper, virtual screening was successfully used to identify five new FDA approved candidate molecules similar to the efavirenz scaffold, and their binding affinity was superior to the native ligand in the active pocket of the COVID-19 main protease, i.e.; podophyllotoxin, oxacillin, lovastatin, simvastatin, and gefitinib. The re-docked results after MD simulation revealed an increase in the binding affinity of simvastatin and lovastatin (8.2 and 7.9 kcal/mol), respectively. Notably, there was a decrease in the binding affinity of podophyllotoxin (7.7 kcal/mol), and the binding affinity of oxacillin and gefitinib (7.7 kcal/mol) remained constant. The docking results showed that H-bonds and hydrophobic interactions might play important roles in contributing to the molecular interactions between the active compounds and the COVID-19 main protease. The DFT calculations and molecular docking showed that lovastatin and simvastatin may be considered as potential hits as anti-coronavirus agents and can be selected for further studies like modification of the scaffold, characterization, and <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation. The predicted physiochemical and ADMET parameters were within the acceptable optimal requirements for drug development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec5">
      <title>Declarations</title>
      <sec id="sec5.1">
        <title>Author contribution statement</title>
        <p id="p0135">Maryam Amra Jordaan: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p>
        <p id="p0140">Oluwakemi Ebenezer: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p>
        <p id="p0145">Nkululeko Damoyi, Michael Shapi: Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec5.2">
        <title>Funding statement</title>
        <p id="p0150">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec5.3">
        <title>Competing interest statement</title>
        <p id="p0155">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec5.4">
        <title>Additional information</title>
        <p id="p0160">No additional information is available for this paper.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="cebib0010">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref1">
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pharmaceutical-technology.com/news/who-forum-coronavirus-vaccine/" id="intref0020">https://www.pharmaceutical-technology.com/news/who-forum-coronavirus-vaccine/</ext-link>
          <year>2020</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref2">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Contini</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Virtual Screening of an FDA Approved Drugs Database on Two COVID-19 Coronavirus Proteins</chapter-title>
          <year>2020</year>
          <comment>ChemRxiv. Preprint</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref3">
          <source>WHO Situation Report 66, March 26th</source>
          <year>2020</year>
          <comment>(Accessed on 27 March 2020)</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Clercq</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Therapeutic options for the 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV)</article-title>
          <source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <year>2020</year>
          <fpage>149</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32127666</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref5">Y. Li, J. Zhang, N. Wang, H. Li, Y. Shi, G. Guo, K. Liu, H. Zeng, Q. Zou, Therapeutic drugs targeting 2019-nCoV main protease by high-throughput screening. BioRxiv Preprint 2020.01.28.922922.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref6">X. Liu, B. Zhang, Z. Jin, H. Yang, Z. Rao, The crystal structure of 2019-nCoV main protease in complex with an inhibitor N3.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref7">
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thesouthafrican.com/lifestyle/health-fitness/coronavirus-thailand-drug-cocktail-february-2020/" id="intref0030">https://www.thesouthafrican.com/lifestyle/health-fitness/coronavirus-thailand-drug-cocktail-february-2020/</ext-link>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>V.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hung</surname>
              <given-names>I.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>K.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of lopinavir/ritonavir in the treatment of SARS: initial virological and clinical findings</article-title>
          <source>Thorax</source>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>252</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14985565</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref9">B. R. Beck, B. Shin,Y. Choi, S. Park, K. Kang,Predicting commercially available antiviral drugs that may act on the novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV), Wuhan, China through a drug-target interaction deep learning model. BioRxiv (Unpublished results) preprint.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shaha</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Modia</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saga</surname>
              <given-names>S.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>In silico studies on therapeutic agents for COVID-19: drug repurposing approach</article-title>
          <source>Life Sci.</source>
          <volume>252</volume>
          <year>2020</year>
          <fpage>117652</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32278693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shinxy</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parky</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kangzy</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hox</surname>
              <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Self-attention based molecule representation for predicting drug-target interaction</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Mach. Learn. Res.</source>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <year>2019</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref12">
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.vanguardngr.com/2020/02/china-begins-clinical-trials-for-new-arv-to-treat-coronavirus/" id="intref0035">https://www.vanguardngr.com/2020/02/china-begins-clinical-trials-for-new-arv-to-treat-coronavirus/</ext-link>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref13">PubChem [Internet]. Bethesda (MD): National Library of Medicine (US), National Center for Biotechnology Information; 2004-. PubChem Compound Summary for CID 5362440, Indinavir; [cited 2020 Aug. 10]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/Indinaviris" id="intref0010a">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/Indinaviris</ext-link> from the NIH National library of Medicine.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref14">
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.drugs.com/monograph/atazanavir-sulfate.html" id="intref0045">https://www.drugs.com/monograph/atazanavir-sulfate.html</ext-link>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>B.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cobicistat (GS-9350): a potent and selective inhibitor of human CYP3A as a novel pharmacoenhancer</article-title>
          <source>ACS Med. Chem. Lett.</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24900196</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Waters</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The use of caspofungin in HIV-infected individuals</article-title>
          <source>Expet Opin. Invest. Drugs</source>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>899</fpage>
          <lpage>908</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Good</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Virtual screening</article-title>
          <source>Comp. Med. Chem. II</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>494</lpage>
          <comment>In this issue</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref18">
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zinc.docking.org" id="intref0050">https://zinc.docking.org</ext-link>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref19">
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org" id="intref0055">www.rcsb.org</ext-link>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trott</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olson</surname>
              <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vina</surname>
              <given-names>AutoDock</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improving the speed and accuracy of docking with a new scoring function, efficient optimization, and multithreading</article-title>
          <source>J.&#xA0;Comput. Chem.</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>461</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19499576</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mehrbod</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Omar</surname>
              <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hair-Bejo</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haghani</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ideris</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanisms of action and efficacy of statins against influenza</article-title>
          <source>BioMed Res. Int.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Romero-P&#xE9;rez</surname>
              <given-names>A.I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ibern-G&#xF3;mez</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamuela-Ravent&#xF3;s</surname>
              <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de la Torre-Boronat</surname>
              <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piceid</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The major resveratrol derivative in grape juices</article-title>
          <source>Agric. Food Chem.</source>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>1533</fpage>
          <lpage>1536</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ardalani</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Avan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghayour-Mobarhan</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Podophyllotoxin: a novel potential natural anticancer agent</article-title>
          <source>Avicenna J. Phytomed.</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2017</year>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28884079</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weng</surname>
              <given-names>T.-C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kao Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y.-H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>S.-J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tai</surname>
              <given-names>S.-H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A&#xA0;systematic review and meta-analysis on the therapeutic equivalence of statins</article-title>
          <source>J.&#xA0;Clin. Pharm. Therapeut.</source>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>151</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>V.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martins</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suppo de Souza Rugolo</surname>
              <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Lourdes Ribeiro de Souza da Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of oxacillin resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from the neonatal and pediatric units of a Brazilian teaching hospital</article-title>
          <source>Clin. Med. Pediatr.</source>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23818792</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muhsin</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graham</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirkpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gefitinib</article-title>
          <source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>515</fpage>
          <lpage>516</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12841190</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>